Guide to the Sir Francis Cowley Burnand Punch magazine correspondence, 1861-1908 MS 130
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Sir Francis Cowley Burnand Punch magazine correspondence
1861-1908
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Burnand, F. C. (Francis Cowley), 1836-1917
MS 130
0.25 Linear Feet (49 letters)
This collection contains forty-nine letters from Sir Francis Cowley Burnand, British editor of "Punch" magazine,to various people he worked with. The letters span the years 1861-1908
Biographical Note
Sir Francis Cowley Burnand (1836-1917), was a talented and prolific comedic writer. He began writing stage pieces while at Eton College from 1851-1854. He then moved on to Trinity College, Cambridge University, for three years. He entered the seminary soon after, but decided his true vocation was as a comedic writer for the stage. Burnand authored over one hundered farces, burlesques, pantomimes, light musical pieces, and melodramas. He collaborated with both W.S. Gilbert and Arthur Sullivan. He also wrote for the comic periodical "Fun." Mark Lemon, the founding editor of "Punch," recruited him as a regular contributor in 1863. Burnand worked at "Punch" for forty-three years. He was knighted in 1902 - the first time a "Punch" writer had been so honored. After his forced retirement from the magazine in 1906, Burnand toured England with a lecture entitled "Nearly Fifty Years of Punch." His memoirs, titled "Records and Reminiscences," were published in 1903.
Biographical information excerpted from "Encyclopedia of British Humorists, Geoffrey Chaucer to John Cleese," volume 1, A-K., page 169. Garland Publishing, New York and London, 1996.
Scope and Contents
Sir Francis Cowley Burnand was the editor of "Punch" magazine. His correspondence was directed to the people he worked with and usually concerned the literary material he dealt with. Correspondents include Sir Henry Thompson, the surgeon; Sir F. Carruthers Gould, Mrs. Merivale, Gerald Christy the lecture agent, and others. The letters, which span most of his working life, dealt with Roman Catholicism, Daphne du Maurier, the "Punch" cartoon titled "Dropping the Pilot", Sir Francis' much protested forced "Punch," his plays and their performances, his lectures, life and career.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased from Mr. Myers, bookdealer, and received May 9, 1958.
Index Terms
Subjects
English wit and humor; Poets, English -- 19th century; Humorists, English -- 19th century
Subjects (Persons)
Burnand, F. C. (Francis Cowley), 1836-1917
- Series I: Francis C. Burnand Punch magazine correspondence, 1861-1908
  Scope and Contents note
  Some items had no indication of date or addressee. In such cases, the first few words of text or return address, if any,is given for identification.
  - Francis Cowley Burnand to Lacy, November 1, 1861 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Lacy, April 7, 1867 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Lacy, April 28, 1867 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to "Dear Pal", December 17, 1869 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to L. Sleure, December 22, 1877 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to P. Simpson, June 9, 1878 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to "Dear Sir", October 14, 1878 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to "Dear Charles", June 30, 1879 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Carolus, march 13, 1880 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to "Dear Pal", February 20, 1882 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to "Dear Charles", May 3, 1882 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Mrs. Skinner, December 10, 1884 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Sir Henry Thompson, july 9, 1885 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to ----, June 20, 1889 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to The Lecture Agency, may 13,1892 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to My Dear Seymour, March 15, 1897 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Percy Reeve, June 9, 1899 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to My Dear Mr. Gould, January 12, 1900 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to My Dear Mr. Gould, November 3, 1900 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to J.W. Rogers, November 28, 1901 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to My Dear Mrs. Merivale, May 26, 1902 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Mr. Gould, Februrary 16, 1906 (Folder 1)
    - Francis C. Burnand to G. Christy, January 20, 1903 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Mr. Gould, February 16, 1906 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Mr. Christy, May 2,1906 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Gerald Christy, May 15,1906 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Mr. Christy, May 20,1906 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Mr. Christy, May 25,1906 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Mr. Christy, June 3,1906 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Gerald Christy, November 2,1906 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Gerald Christy, March 21,1908 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Gerald Christy, March 22,1908 (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Dear Brondly, February 9---- (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to "Gwendolyn (sp?)my dear", February 4---- (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to O'Conan Power, March 1---- (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Herman, March 16---- (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Mr. Gerald Christy, March 29---- (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Mr.Christy, May 22----'My dear Mr. Christy, thanks for your letter..." (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Mr.Christy, May 28----note marked Private, May 28, 18 Royal Crescent, Ramsgate (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to ----, May 28----,note marked 18 Royal Crescent, Ramsgate (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to ----, May 29----, note, "Kindly compare list..." (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Dear Charles, undated (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Sir Henry (Thompson?), marked 192 Brompton Road, undated (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Mr.Lacy, "Your letter has been forwarded to me...", undated (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand, note marked "Private", undated (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Dear Lacy, marked 102 Belgrave Road, undated (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Mr. Lacy, marked 8 Sussex Place, Hyde Park, undated---- (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand to Dear Mr. Lacy, marked 88 High Street, Eton, undated (Folder 1)
  - Francis C. Burnand "Excellent Letter! Excellent News!, undated (Folder 1)